Finding Aid for Rose Parker Kleinman Papers 1947-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rose Parker Kleinman papers 1947-1977, 1964-1977
Kleinman, Rose Parker, 1914-1977.
2 linear feet
Detroit, Michigan, social activist and reformer. Correspondence and subject files relating to her interest in cooperatives, especially organizations concerned with low-income, open housing projects; also photographs and audio-tapes.
861024 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 7197 ) was acquired from Dr. Janet Kleinman Baum (daughter) and from Mr. Jonathan Rose (family friend) in April 1985.
The collection is open for research.
Rose Parker Kleinman, social activist and reformer, was born in 1914 in Des Moines, Iowa, of Russian immigrant parents. She attended public schools in Cleveland, and went to Bryn Mawr College where she was enrolled in the Workers Education Project.
While attending high school and college, Kleinman became active in the youth division of the Socialist Party. During later activities for the party, she met and married Robert Parker. The couple worked actively for the Socialist cause in both Cleveland and New York, and were important participants in the presidential campaign efforts of Norman Thomas. In 1945, several years after they moved to Pennsylvania, Robert Parker died unexpectedly. Rose and her one-year old daughter, Janet Ilene, moved to Boston to be near Rose's mother. Rose resumed her work for the Socialist Party, was involved in the trade union movement and wrote a column for the local CIO paper (CIO News), and served as executive director (19471950) of the Boston office of the Jewish Labor Committee for which she undertook investigations into racial discrimination.
In 1950, Rose met and married Dr. Shmarya Kleinman, a Socialist and Jewish leader in Detroit. She moved there, where her son, Joseph Mandell, was born in 1952, and continued her involvement in social causes. Her interest in eliminating discrimination led to her involvement in the Fair Housing Listing Service which assisted Blacks to move into previously all white areas. She worked with organizations and cooperatives that sponsored low-income, open housing, such as the Michigan Housing Associates, Equal Housing Opportunities, and Housing Opportunities Made Equal Services. She served as housing consultant to the Washington-based Foundation for Cooperative Housing (FCH), and midwest field secretary for the National Association of Housing Cooperatives. Much of her work in the field of housing culminated in her successful fight for the passage of the legislation that established the Michigan State Housing Authority. She drew on her extensive experience and interest in cooperatives of all types to teach classes at area universities and colleges. As she neared the end of her life, she became quite interested in the concept of workers' cooperatives. She died at her daughter's home in Ann Arbor, Michigan, on July 22, 1977.
The Rose Parker Kleinman papers are almost entirely those from her years in Detroit and are limited in quantity (2 linear feet). They can be used by the researcher interested in compiling a short biographical study of the last twenty years of her life, or in the activities of one of the many white liberals in Detroit in the 1960s who promoted racial equality. They provide an introduction to the cooperative movement as a whole and in the state of Michigan in the 1960s and 1970s, and to the activities of one of the leaders in the field. Finally, the papers on low-income, open housing organizations in Detroit in the 1960s and 1970s can provide a limited supplement to those found in other libraries, such as the Mayor's Papers in the Burton Library in Detroit. There is very little in the collection, however, on Kleinman's efforts to have established the Michigan State Housing Authority. The researcher should approach the collection with the understanding that no one area or organization can be studied in depth, but that the character, ideas, and personality of Rose Kleinman are evident throughout the collection.
The Kleinman papers are arranged in five series: Personal; Correspondence; Cooperatives; Housing; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Civil rights--Michigan.; Cooperative societies--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Discrimination in housing--Michigan.; Housing--Michigan.; Social reformers--Michigan--Detroit.; Women social reformers--Michigan--Detroit.; Kleinman, Rose Parker, 1914-1977.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Activists.; Kleinman, Rose Parker, 1914-1977.; Women.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Personal
  The Personal series contains biographical information, materials from Kleinman's two European trips (1966, 1975) on which she studied different types of European housing projects and cooperatives, clippings of her columns from the CIO News from 1948-1949, and various of her speeches and writings. Although many of the latter are in handwritten outline form, there are completed ones that demonstrate the depth of Kleinman's commitment to housing and worker-owned cooperatives, and racial equality.
  - Background (mostly letters of recommendation and resumes) (Box 1)
  - European Trips 1966, 1975 (Box 1)
    (handwritten notes, schedules, itineraries, memorandums, correspondence)
  - "Fair Play or Foul" 1948-1949 (Box 1)
    (clippings of Kleinman's column for the CIO News)
  - Speeches/Writings, 2 folders (Box 1)
    includes many handwritten notes
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series consists of incoming and outgoing letters primarily from the years 1965-1977. There is a general file arranged chronologically, followed by files arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent. The correspondence mostly concerns Kleinman's interest in cooperatives, both in the United States and abroad. She would often receive advice and progress reports from leaders in the field in Europe and would describe her own efforts in this country.
  - General undated, 1947, 1959, 1965-1977 (Box 1)
  - Derrick, Paul (The Coop Party, London, England) 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Dreyer, Stanley (President, Cooperative League of the USA) 1971, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Housing and Urban Development 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    (Correspondence re: funding for projects)
  - Laidlaw, A.F. (Central Mortgage and Housing Corporation-Canada) 1972, 1973, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Rose, Bonnie (Proaction, Inc., Canada) 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Voorhis, Jerry Undated, 1967-1968, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    (contains Kleinman letter on Detroit race riot, 1967)
  - Wilcox, Roger 1959, 1965, 1968 (Box 1)
- Cooperatives
  The Cooperatives series contains materials which document Kleinman's teaching activities; the work of the Ferndale Cooperative, Inc., in which she actively participated; the activities of the various housing cooperative organizations with which she was associated; and her interest in workers' cooperatives. The files are rather fragmentary and more likely to demonstrate the breadth of her work, rather than supply many detailed specifics.
  - Background, 3 folders (Box 1)
    pamphlets, brochures, reprints, etc. re: local and national coops
  - Academic Courses
    - General, early 1970s (Box 1)
      (includes syllabi, and handwritten lecture outlines and notes on classes given at local colleges)
    - Committee Meetings 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      (correspondence and minutes of the Michigan Cooperative School Committee Volunteers)
    - Correspondence 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      mostly re: arrangements for classes
    - Finances 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      (materials re: obtaining finances to conduct classes)
  - Ferndale Cooperative, Inc. 1960s-1970s, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (includes correspondence, reports, and minutes re: housing and credit union)
  - Housing
    - Foundation for Cooperative Housing Services, Inc. 1965-1970 (Box 1)
      (subsidiary of the FCH-mostly documents from national organization, but includes proposals for Michigan housing projects)
    - Legislation 1967, 1969, 1976 (Box 1)
      (summaries, bills, correspondence re: state and national laws)
    - Michigan housing Associates 1964-1971 (Box 1)
      (includes articles of incorporation, minutes, bylaws, correspondence, project reports)
    - National Association of Housing Cooperatives, undated 1968 (Box 1)
      (correspondence re: NAHC activities, and conference proceedings)
    - Prefabricated Housing 1968-1971 (Box 2)
      (mostly correspondence re: attempts to establish such in Michigan)
    - Rehabilitation Housing, undated 1960s, 1975 (Box 2)
      (mostly correspondence re: proposed projects)
    - Senior Citizens 1960s, 1970s (Box 2)
      (includes correspondence, drafts of ideas/proposals, minutes, and legislation)
    - Student (Box 2)
      (chiefly background type materials on student housing coops in Michigan and other states)
  - Workers' Cooperatives 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    (proposal and correspondence)
- Housing (mostly re: Detroit)
  Materials from nonprofit organizations which tried to sponsor low-income, open housing projects can be found in the Housing series but are not of sufficient quantity to allow organizational histories to be compiled.
  - Background 1950s, 1960s, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Equal Housing Opportunities 1966-1969, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (includes minutes, handwritten notes, tax exemption materials, and correspondence)
  - Fair Housing Listing Service undated, 1966 (Box 2)
    (proposals, correspondence, and handwritten notes)
  - Greater Detroit Fair Housing, Inc. 1965, 1967 (Box 2)
    (bylaws, correspondence re: open housing)
  - Housing Opportunities Made Equal Services 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    (H.O.M.E.S.; bylaws, proposal for, Board of Directors meeting minutes)
  - Michigan Welfare League 1969 (Box 2)
    (correspondence re: housing handbook)
  - Model Cities 1969 (Box 2)
    (correspondence, proposed programs and changes)
  - New Detroit Committee 1968 (Box 2)
    (mostly handwritten notes on seminar "Creating An Open Society")
  - New Towns undated (Box 2)
    (slide presentation scripts re: European Study tour of New Towns)
- Miscellaneous
  The final series, Miscellaneous includes folders of Kleinman's notebooks, a scattering of photographs, and audio tapes.
  - Notebooks, etc., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Audio-tapes of cooperative housing breakfast meeting sponsored by the Wayne County AFL-CIO, Jerry Voorhis, principal speaker August 11, 1964, 3 7" inch reels (Box 2)